<chapter xml:id="chapter-transactional-references">
    <title>Transactional References (in progress)</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            In Multiverse all coordinated state changes need to be done through transactional references. These references
            can be compared to the java.util.concurrent.atomic references, except that they can participate in txns.
            So if you have worked with these references before, it shouldn't be too hard to grasp. Check out the following
            code fragment:
         <programlisting language="java">

    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;

    public class Account{
        private final IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);
        private final Ref&lt;Date&gt; lastModified = newRef(new Date());

        ...
    }
        </programlisting>
        Changes made on the amount and lastModified ref are coordinated through a txn where all changes happen
        isolated and are consistent. It is best to make these fields final, since they should not be changed after
        creation.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Types</title>
        <para>
            There aren't different types of transactional refs. Some are optimized for primitive types, while the
            'Ref' is optimized for object references:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>IntRef: a transactional ref for primitive int.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>BooleanRef: a transactional refs for the primitive boolean.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LongRef: a transactional ref for the primitive long.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DoubleRef: a transactional ref for the primitive double.</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
                   <para>Ref: a transactional ref for storing a object reference.</para>
                 </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            The advantage of the primitive types is that they not only have methods only useful for their specific type (like increment)
            but also that they prevent unwanted autoboxing. Generating millions of objects per second, just kills performance and
            scalability.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Atomic methods</title>
        <para>
            The different ref implementation also expose atomic methods like atomicGet/atomicSet (and many more). These methods
            automatically run under their own 'txn' and ignoring the current txn if one is available. Atomic methods
            are very fast since a lot of overhead of the txn is removed.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Commute</title>
        <para>
            It is important to realize that although certain operations commute, e.g. the add or multiply, but they don't have to commute with
            each other. So be careful when combining different commuting operations.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Alter</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Blocking methods</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </sect1>


</chapter>