<chapter xml:id="chapter-introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sect1>
<title>Traditional Concurrency Control (in progress)</title>
<para>
    Traditional concurrency control is complex because you need to worry about a lot of problems. First of all you need to make sure
    that the program does no bad things (so no race problems), and you also need to worry about that good things happen eventually (
    so no deadlocks, livelocks or starvation). Lock based concurrency control is well known but also dreaded because even simple code
    can very quickly become too complex to reason about.
</para>

<para>
    The idea behind Software Transactional Memory (STM), is that a database like programming model can be provided on in memory datastructures.
    The STM is going to worry about read/write inconsistencies, deadlocks etc and makes sure that all changes make it or none make it. To give
    you an example:
</para>
<programlisting language="java">

    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;

    public class Account{
        private final IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);

        public void transfer(final int a){
            execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                    amount.increment(a);
                }
            });
        }

        public int getAmount(){
            execute(new AtomicIntClosure()){
                public int execute(Transaction tx){
                    return amount.get();
                }
            });
        }
    }
</programlisting>
<para>
    As you can see, the Account class has a single field 'amount' which is of class IntRef; a transactional reference. All reads/writes
    on this ref are coordinated and perhaps tracked by the txn. The logic of both methods is captured in an AtomicClosure. There
    are different types of Closures for the different return types. There are also primitive versions that prevent unwanted autoboxing.
    An AtomicClosure is executed by an AtomicBlock (in our case this AtomicBlock is stored in the StmUtils and exposed through the
    execute methods.
</para>

<para>
    In the previous example, only a single field was updated, but there are no restructions in the number of fields. If you want you could add more:
</para>
    <programlisting language="java">
        import org.multiverse.api.*;
        import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
        import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;

        public class Account{
            final private IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);
            final private Ref date = newRef(new Date());

            public void transfer(final int a){
                execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                    public void execute(Transaction tx){
                        amount.increment(a);
                        lastModifiedDate.set(new Date());
                    }
                });
            }

            public Date getLastModifiedDate(){
                execute(new AtomicClosure()){
                    public Date execute(Transaction tx){
                        return lastModifiedDate.get();
                    }
                });
            }

            public int getAmount(){
                execute(new AtomicIntClosure()){
                    public int execute(Transaction tx){
                        return amount.get();
                    }
                });
            }
        }
    </programlisting>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Composition</title>
    <para>
        Transactions can be composed
    </para>
</sect1>

</chapter>