<chapter xml:id="chapter-deferred-and-compensating-tasks">

    <title>Deferred and compensating tasks (in progress)</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            When a Multiverse transaction is used, all changes made to transactional references during that transactions
            are either committed or aborted. So it won't happen that changes of an uncommitted transaction ever become
            visible in another transaction. But in some cases you need to execute logic that is not managed by a
            transaction, e.g. cleaning up resources. This can be done using:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Deferred tasks: executed after transaction commit</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Compensating tasks: executed after transaction abort</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            In Multiverse there are 2 different tastes of deferred and compensating actions:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    normal tasks: these tasks are registered during the execution of the transaction,
                    and are automatically cleared on transaction commit/abort. This type of task is useful,
                    if it depends on logic executed during the execution of the transaction.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    permanent tasks: these tasks are registered when the org.multiverse.api.TransactionExecutor is created.
                    The advantage of permanent tasks is that they don't need to be registered
                    every time the transaction runs, so there is a lot less overhead (especially gc). Permanent listeners
                    are also useful if Multiverse needs to be integrated in other systems/languages so that integration
                    logic can be executed.
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Normal compensating task</title>
        <para>
            When a transaction commits, using the normal compensating tasks, additional logic can be executed after the
            commit of the transaction.
        <programlisting language="java">
    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

    public class Foo{

        public void foo(){
            execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                     ... logic

                     scheduleDeferredTask(new Runnable()){
                        public void run(){
                            System.out.println("Transaction committed");
                        }
                     });

                    ... more logic
                }
            });
        }

        ...
    }
        </programlisting>
        The StmUtils.scheduleDeferredTask forwards to the Transaction.register(TransactionListener) method and uses the Transaction
        stored on the ThreadLocalTransaction. Normal compensating tasks are always executed in the order they were registered.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Normal deferred task</title>
       <para>
            When a transaction aborts, using the normal compensating tasks, additional logic can be executed after the
            abort of the transaction.
        <programlisting language="java">
    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

    public class Foo{

        public void foo(){
            execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                     ... logic

                     scheduleCompensatingTask(new Runnable()){
                        public void run(){
                            System.out.println("Transaction aborted");
                        }
                     });

                    ... more logic
                }
            });
        }

        ...
    }
        </programlisting>
        The StmUtils.scheduleCompensatingTask forwards to the Transaction.register(TransactionListener) method and uses the Transaction
        stored on the ThreadLocalTransaction. Normal compensating tasks are always executed in the order they are registered.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Permanent deferred task</title>
        <para>
            In some cases you want logic to be executed after a Transaction commits. This can be done using a
            compensating task.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="java">

        </programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Permanent compensating task</title>
        <para>
            In some cases you want logic to be executed after a Transaction fails. This can be done using a deferred
            task.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="java">

        </programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>org.multiverse.api.lifecycle.TransactionListener</title>
        <para>

        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Execution order</title>
    </sect1>
</chapter>