<chapter xml:id="chapter-propagation">

    <title>Propagation</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            It can happen that AtomicBlocks are called within the execution of other AtomicBlock and this leads to
            txn nesting. In a lot of cases you want to allow this, but in some cases you want to control it.
            This can be done by config the txn propagation.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>PropagationLevel</title>
        <para>
            Multiverse supports propagation by setting the correct PropagationLevel on the TransactionFactoryBuilder
            (defaults to PropagationLevel.Requires). The following propagation levels are supported:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PropagationLevel.RequiresNew: Indicates that a new txn always is started, even when
                        there is an active txn. The active txn is postponed and used again after the
                        nested txn commits. It could be that the outer txn conflicts made on changes
                        by the inner txn.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PropagationLevel.Requires: Indicates that a new txn will be used if none exists. If
                        one exists, the logic will lift on that txn. This is the default propagation level
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PropagationLevel.Supports: Indicates that it the logic can either be run with or without
                        txn.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PropagationLevel.Never: Indicates that no active txn should be available. If a
                        txn is found, a org.multiverse.api.exceptions.TxnNotAllowedException is thrown.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PropagationLevel.Mandatory: Indicates that a txn should always be available. If not, a
                        org.multiverse.api.exceptions.TxnMandatoryException is thrown.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            An example of configuring the propagation level:

            <programlisting language="java">

    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

    public class Account{
         private final static AtomicBlock transferBlock = getGlobalStmInstance()
              .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
              .setPropagationLevel(PropagationLevel.Requires)
              .newAtomicBlock();

         private final IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);

         public void transfer(final int a){
            transferBlock.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                    amount.incrementAndGet(tx, a);
                }
            });
         }

         ...
    }

            </programlisting>
            In this example the transfer method will lift on an already running txn, but if none is found,
            it will use it own.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Warning</title>
        <para>
            Atm there are no checks if outer AtomicBlock violates the inner AtomicBlock. If the inner AtomicBlock is configured
            as readonly and the outer as an update txn, an outer txn is able to make updates.
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>