<chapter xml:id="chapter-gammastm">

    <title>GammaStm</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            The new GammaStm (the default instance of the Stm interface, and stored in the GlobalStm) is a complete
            rewrite
            of the AlphaStm. The AlphaStm was based on the TL2 design of David Dice with some optimizations. But having
            a central
            clock (an AtomicLong) as a hidden contention point that makes is harder to writer scalable transactional
            datastructures.
            The new GammaStm make use of a conflict counter (comparable to that used in the SkySTM) which only is
            increased on conflict.
            This means that this conflict counter only needs to be increased if there are conflict, and not just on
            every write. Which
            means that the total pressure on the conflict counter will always be equal or smaller than that of the TL2
            design.
        </para>

        <para>
            Not only the fundamental design of the STM has been improved, also a very large effort was made
            in preventing unjustifiably overhead. E.g. virtual method calls (prevent inlining), switch case statements
            (causes problems with branch predication) etc. So a lot of stuff has been optimized and the code is not always
            as pretty.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Orec</title>
        <para>
            Each transactional reference has a ownership record (just an long). Using bit-tweaking a lot of information
            can be stored here:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        surplus: so the number of current readers
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        readonly count: so the number of transaction that have only read and not updated the
                        transactional reference.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        read/update biased: if the orec is read or update biased.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        lock information: readlock (so the number of transaction that acquired the read-lock),
                        write-lock and exclusive-lock.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            So a lot of operations like doing an arrive/depart or acquiring a lock, can all be done by a single cas.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>No Garbage</title>
        <para>
            One of the causes of a not scalable STM is that a lot of garbage is created. The new GammaStm is able to
            reuse a lot of objects (so it pools internally) for almost all transactions. The only object that needs to
            be created is the AtomicClosure. If you can even pool that, then there will be zero waste.
        </para>

        <para>
            One of techniques used to deal with the primitive types and the reference type, is that code is generated
            using Velocity. So the logic only needs to be written once, and the Java code that is optimized for a certain
            type is generated. There is no runtime dependency on Velocity.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Read consistency</title>
        <para>
            The new GammaStm uses 1 basic mechanism for providing read consistency. The basic mechanism is based is on
            semi visible reads (so it is visible that other transactions have read the data, but not which ones). When
            a transaction reads a ref, it increments the surplus, and when the transaction is done with it (so aborts or
            commits), automatically a depart is done. When a transaction commits, and finds that there are reading
            threads,
            it increments the global conflict counter (which in the future probably will be striped). When a reading
            transaction
            sees that the global conflict counter has changed, it does a full conflict scan. Transactions used by the
            GammaStm
            always use readtracking.
        </para>

        <para>
            2 Very important optimizations have been added to this design.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Read biased references: if references are only read, they can become read biased. Once they
                        have
                        become read biased, no arrives/departs are required. So if you have a tree for example, the
                        roots of the
                        tree will no change very often, but without read biased references, they still require an
                        arrive/depart, which
                        in turn limits scalability. If they have become readbiased, and an update is done, the global
                        conflict counter
                        will always be increased and all transactions are forced to do a full conflict scan. Once a ref
                        is written,
                        it automatically become update biased until a certain number of reads have been done.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Always do a full conflict scan: short transactions (so ranging to 20 refs.. this value is
                        configurable)
                        always do a full conflict scan. It should expensive, but in most cases it will only cause some
                        volatile reads.
                        The advantage of using this approach is that a short transaction never needs to do an
                        arrive/depart and never
                        cause the global conflict counter to increment. If only short transactions are used, independant
                        datastructure
                        will scale independently.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Other features</title>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Pessimistic transactions</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Propagation level</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Isolation level</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Commute</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>...</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

