<chapter xml:id="chapter-pessimistic-locking">

    <title>Pessimistic Locking (in progress)</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            Normally STM's are very optimistic, so this means that a transaction can fail when it commits because
            anothertransaction has updated data it has read. When this happens, a
            org.multiverse.api.exceptions.ControlFlowError is thrown (in this case a org.multiverse.api.exceptions.ReadWriteConflict),
            which is caught by the org.multiverse.api.TxnExecutor and the transaction is retried. In some cases the optimistic nature
            can be problematic and something more pessimistic is needed. Multiverse provides support for pessimistic behavior on the
            Ref level using the Ref.getLock or on the Transaction level by setting the readLockMode or writeLockMode.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Lock modes</title>
        <para>
            The Lock has 4 different Lock modes:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>LockMode.None: no pessimistic lock is acquired</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>LockMode.Read: a readlock is acquired that prevents other transactions from acquiring a
                            writelock or exclusive lock, but it still always others to read.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>LockMode.Write: a writelock is acquired that prevents other transactions from acquiring
                            the
                            readlock/writelock or exclusive lock. But it is important to realize that others still are
                            allowed
                            to read it.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>LockMode.Exclusive: an exclusive lock is acquired that prevents other transactions from
                            acquiring any form of lock or do any reads/wites.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Lock upgrade</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Pessimistic locking on ref level</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Pessimistic locking on transaction level</title>
        <para>
            Pessimistic locking can be done on all reads made by a transaction by configuring the
        </para>
    </sect1>

</chapter>