<chapter xml:id="chapter-performance-tuning">

<title>Performance tuning</title>

<sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        This chapter contains various tips for improving performance of transactional datastructures.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Primitive refs</title>
    <para>
        Multiverse provides support for various primitives refs: IntRef, LongRef, BooleanRef and DoubleRef. Using a primitive instead of a
        normal ref in combination with wrapper types, has the advantage that no autoboxing is needed. Doing millions of wrapper creations per
        second, can seriously limit performance and scalability.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Don't throw away the AtomicBlock</title>
    <para>
        It is best to create an AtomicBlock once and stored it in a final static field. For more information see
        'Customize the AtomicBlock'.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Customize the AtomicBlock</title>
    <para>
        Use a customized AtomicBlock, so instead of using this:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="java">

    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;

    public class Account{
        private final IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);

        public void transfer(final int a){
            execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                    amount.increment(a);
                }
            });
        }

        ...
    }
    </programlisting>
    <para>
        Use the following:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="java">
    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

    public class Account{
        private final static AtomicBlock transferBlock = getGlobalStmInstance()
            .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
            .newAtomicBlock();

        private final IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);

        public void transfer(final int a){
            transferBlock.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                    amount.increment(a);
                }
            });
        }

        ...
    }
    </programlisting>
    <para>
        The transferBlock can be placed in a static field and can safely be shared between threads (it is completely threadsafe and designed
        to be used in this way). The advantage of this approach, is that the Stm is able to learn based on previous transaction executions and
        select the best performing settings. It relies on a speculative configuration mechanism where the system starts with the cheapest
        settings, but upgrades to more expensive one if the bet failed. If the AtomicBlock is discarded after usage, the STM will never be able to
        learn. Another problem is that it also causes a lot of GC overhead. So reuse your AtomicBlocks!
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Short transactions</title>
<para>
    Transactions should be kept as short as possible. If the executes over a longer period, chances increase that it runs into a read/write
    conflict. When this happens, a lot of work is lost and needs to be redone. It also could lead to livelock problems.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Small transactions</title>
<para>
    Transactions should be as small as possible, so the less it needs to track, the faster it will be. Also when small transactions are used,
    Multiverse is able to use special optimized transactions that cause less overhead than longer transactions. Another advantage of using
    small transactions, is that the mechanism for providing a read consistent view gets a lot cheaper (if the GammaStm is used). This reduces
    the pressure on the shared conflict counter.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Use atomic methods</title>
    <para>
        If only a single ref needs to be read or written, consider using one the atomic methods that the refs support. They all support atomicGet,
        atomicWeakGet, atomicSet and atomicGetAndSet. Atomic method provide the same guarantees and functionality you normally have with transactions,
        but the overhead of transactions is considerably lower.
    </para>
</sect1>


<sect1>
    <title>Explicit transaction passing</title>
    <para>
        Normally a Transaction doesn't need to be passed explicitly, because it is placed in the org.multiverse.api.ThreadLocalTransaction. Every time
        the transaction is needed, it needs to be read from this ThreadLocal. By passing the Transaction explicitly, this overhead is removed.
    <programlisting language="java">

    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

    public class Account{
        private final static AtomicBlock transferBlock = getGlobalStmInstance()
            .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
            .newAtomicBlock();

        private final IntRef amount = newIntRef(0);

        public void transfer(final int a){
            transferBlock.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                    amount.increment(tx, a);
                }
            });
        }

        ...
    }
    </programlisting>
        As you can see, the increment method now has an explicit transaction. Almost all methods of the ref are overloaded with a version that also
        accepts a Transaction. If your methods call other transactional methods, the transaction can be passed manually, e.g.

    <programlisting language="java">
    import org.multiverse.api.*;
    import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
    import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

    public class Foo{
        private final static AtomicBlock someBlock = getGlobalStmInstance()
                   .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
                   .newAtomicBlock();

        private final IntRef ref = newIntRef(0);

        public void internalMethod(Transaction tx){
           ref.set(tx, 2);
        }

        public void externalMethod(){
            someBlock.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                public void execute(Transaction tx){
                    internalMethod(tx);
                }
            });
        }
    }
    </programlisting>
        Unfortunately this boilerplate code is required as long as the instrumentation is not available in Multiverse. Instrumentation
        can transform this code mechanically. In other JVM based languages like Groovy, Scala, JRuby, this ugliness can be
        tucked away behind some syntactic sugar.
    </para>

</sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Nested transactional methods</title>
        It can happen that nested transactional methods are required, e.g.:
        <para>
            <programlisting language="java">
     import org.multiverse.api.*;
     import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
     import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
     import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

     public class Foo{
         private final static AtomicBlock method1Block = getGlobalStmInstance()
                    .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
                    .newAtomicBlock();
         private final static AtomicBlock method2Block = getGlobalStmInstance()
                    .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
                    .newAtomicBlock();

         private final IntRef ref = newIntRef(0);

         public void method1(){
             method1Block.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                 public void execute(Transaction tx){
                     ref.set(2);
                 }
             });
         }

         public void method2(){
             method2Block.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                 public void execute(Transaction tx){
                     method1();
                 }
             });
         }
     }
         </programlisting>
         The problem with this approach is that 2 AtomicClosures are created when method2 is called. This problem can
         be prevented by creating 2 version of the method; 1 with a transaction and one without. E.g.:
         <programlisting language="java">
     import org.multiverse.api.*;
     import org.multiverse.api.refs.*;
     import static org.multiverse.api.StmUtils.*;
     import static org.multiverse.api.GlobalStmInstance.*

     public class Foo{
         private final static AtomicBlock method1Block = getGlobalStmInstance()
                    .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
                    .newAtomicBlock();
         private final static AtomicBlock method2Block = getGlobalStmInstance()
                    .newTransactionFactoryBuilder()
                    .newAtomicBlock();

         private final IntRef ref = newIntRef(0);

         public void method1(){
             method1Block.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                 public void execute(Transaction tx){
                     method1(tx);
                 }
             });
         }

         public void method1(Transaction tx){
            ref.set(tx, 2);
         }

         public void method2(){
             method2Block.execute(new AtomicVoidClosure()){
                 public void execute(Transaction tx){
                     internalMethod(tx);
                 }
             });
         }

         public void method2(Transaction tx){
             method1(tx);
         }
     }
         </programlisting>
     </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Ref access</title>
    <para>
        Accessing the ref for a read or write costs time (at least if you want to make sure of the methods that participate in transactions).
        So some care should be applied about the number of times a ref is accessed. So if you have the chance to store it in a local variable,
        instead of doing a read/write every time, this will give you better performance.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
    <title>Primitive AtomicClosure</title>
    <para>
        Multiverse provides various forms of AtomicClosures for void, reference and primitive types. The primitive AtomicClosures like the AtomicIntClosure,
        AtomicBooleanClosure, AtomicLongClosure and AtomicDoubleClosure prevent any form of boxing. So if you need to return a int, boolean, long
        or Double, make sure you are using a primitive AtomicClosure.
    </para>
</sect1>

</chapter>